Hello, I'm Lakuse.
And, I'm Tepo.
Right now, we're in San Jose in California in the US,
but what's around us?
This is a Japanese Garden.
A Japanese Garden.
Hm, it's like Japan.
Mhm.
In different countries they do a "garden" in different ways,
but in Japan, they often have water.
In the gardens.
There's also fish in the water.
There's koi and- what color are they?
Red, yellow, white.
Yes, they're beautiful.
When the sun hits them, their scales shine in the sun.
But..
Here, there's a lot of ponds for fish.
But now most of the ponds are drained.
Yeah, I saw that.
That's where the ponds would be,
but there's no water!
No fish at all!
A while ago..
There's only one actual pond right now.
All of the fish are in there.
Everyone's looking at the fish over there.
There's a lot of people here but most of them are over there next to the water.
There's a not lot of fish, but also
the water is all green and has algae all in it.
So you can't really make out a lot of the fish.
I think we've only seen like two fish?
Three of them.
There's also tadpoles too.
They are super small.
Then they grow up into frogs.
So, they are only tadpoles for a little bit, and then they are frogs forever.
There's also birds here.
Annoying birds!
I'm from Canada and there's a really annoying bird there and we call it the..
"Canada Goose"
And it's really terrible and agressive towards people and gets all loud in people's faces.
A little bit ago, one came up to me and tried to fight me.
But they're in California too.
Yeah, it's the California Goose too.
I can't get away from them!
It should be called the California Goose too.
And, I'm in California and right now I'm speaking Toki Pona to Tepo.
Mhm, Mhm.
We both speak Toki Pona.
Right, and..
I forgot to say something.
I forgot to say why all the fish aren't in the ponds.
And why are all of them drained too?
It's because..
A while ago-
There was a creek near here and-
what was it's name again?
It's Coyote Creek.
Ah, okay, it was Coyote Creek.
What happened there was..
It overflowed badly and it ended up flooding,
and ended up damaging the garden.
Or maybe it could have but didn't? I don't really know, but,
Actually, there's a sign over there that talks about the animals around here,
but I haven't really talked about it.
But it says that they want to repair this garden and the creek,
so they can't have too much water around here.
Maybe the infrastructure is broken.
And if they tried to keep it running then it wouldn't work.
The flooding happened in 2017.
And it's 2022 right now, right, so..
Numbers are hard.
Something broke 5 days ago.
Ah, right.
The sign also said that they are hoping to fix it at the end of this year.
So it's taken 5 years to fix it!
That's a lot of work.
These are the trees.
I can get a good angle.
There's also a Japanese house right here.
They said that you used to be able to buy tea from there and a lot of sweets.
But it's closed because they are trying to restore it, so people can't buy things.
Do you know when it closed?
I don't really know, but the website said it was.
We're speaking Toki Pona right now.
I'm speaking Toki Pona with Lakuse and having fun.
It's a lot of fun, but what is Toki Pona?
It's a language. I've used it for long enough so I know it can say stuff using.. good.
"using" good?
using good.
or a good way.
It really improves conversation.
If you talk about something in Toki Pona,
you learn more about it.
I can also use the phrase "if you don't know it fully, you can't say it in Toki Pona"
Me and Tepo try to say really fun and interesting complex things.
But I don't really know them well so I can't really talk about them.
If you want to know if someone really knows something, then try speaking Toki Pona to them!
But.. they might not know Toki Pona.
Sometimes, I try to talk about cooking.
But I really don't know food,
so I can't really talk about it..
I know what the food is called in English, but I can't really explain it in Toki Pona.
Because I don't really know what's in the food.
I have no idea.
And also a lot of things are similar.
A lot of birds are similar, a lot of fruit, so you really want to know the differences.
There's a lot of fruits that are red, sweet and round.
So you really want to know the differences between this fruit and that fruit and so on.
What's important?
There's the one fruit that Eve ate that messed with people, and
there's another fruit that's really juicy.
It's like that, right? You talk about things in different ways.
Toki Pona is a language, and it's really good.
Hm, what else should I talk about?
Maybe why me and Lakuse started to speak Toki Pona and how we learned it.
Like what? Why? For what?
Yeah, we started speaking online.
Mostly people don't speak in person.
Only online.
On Discord. There's a lot of big communities on Discord.
There's also a lot of people on Telegram.
There's also sometimes Toki Pona speakers in the Esperanto community.
The person who made it is an Esperanto speaker.
Sonja made Toki Pona and knew Esperanto for a long time.
So Esperantists found Toki Pona and thought "oh, this could be fun!"
Oh, cool, it's from an Esperanto speaker.
There's also some words that are from Esperanto like
"supa" (table) which is from "surfaco" I think?
Maybe.
That might not be true.
There's tomo (house), pali (work), and selo (outer layer)..
from ŝelo.
I actually don't know Esperanto.
That's not true.
You know some words.
Saluton! (Hello!). I only know that word.
Jes. (Yes.)
These are words in Esperanto!
Yes, and right now..
(Esperanto word)
Right now, we're speaking Toki Pona here and it is really fun.
But I want to do it again soon because a ton of people are having a meetup and speaking Toki Pona together!
Using their mouth, their face and their bodies, all of it.
That could happen.
In Europe, a lot of Toki Pona speakers are planning on having a meetup in Vienna.
Is it just Vin? I don't know.
I think that's how you say it.
It's really soon, I think it's next month?
There can also be other meetups in the future too.
They should be in the US too.
Mhm. I really want a meetup in the US.
A lot of people could come.
There's a lot of Toki Pona speakers in the US, all of them should come and talk together.
Also, we also want more people to learn Toki Pona so it's easier to have meetups.
So learn Toki Pona!
I'm Lakuse.
I'm Tepo.
We can stop recording now?
Goodbye!
English translation by kasi Sonki
There's a fish!